ILGWU Union Health Center Publications 5780/171
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Union Health Center Publications
1911-1978
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Union Health Center
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/171
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Publications (documents).
This collection contains booklets and pamphlets by and about the Union Health Center, as well as some reports of the Joint Board of Sanitary Control.
5512047
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
C. Berne, November 12, 2003
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 15, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
In 1913, the New York City locals of the ILGWU established the Union Health Center (UHC), under the direction of Dr. George Price of the Joint Board of Sanitary Control. Initially, the UHC offered physical exams, medical treatments, access to a dental clinic, and information about health and hygiene. For a period, the center operated through a cooperative plan, with patients paying a fee and the union subsidizing the rest of the cost of the visit. During the Depression, the cost of running the center was met by other means. This included getting other local unions in New York City, such as the electrical workers, metal workers, letter carriers, post office clerks, and pocketbook workers, to affiliate with the UHC, as well as winning an official endorsement from the Central Labor Union of New York. Beginning in the 1940s, New York City manufacturers agreed to contribute to a fund that would cover the cost of medical services provided to members at the UHC.
By the 1960s, the UHC offered comprehensive care to ILGWU members and their families, and over the years, the center's range of services expanded to include social and psychological services, eye exams, maternity care, and surgical consultation. The Union Health Center continues its work today at 275 Seventh Avenue, in New York City.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Union Health Center document the evolving role of the center. Included are general correspondence, meeting minutes of the UHC's medical board, annual reports on the UHC's activities to the General Executive Board, triennial reports to delegates at the ILGWU's international conventions, and related published materials. Much of this material is routine or administrative in nature.
In both collections that comprise the records of the Union Health Center, there are articles by such figures as George M. Price and Pauline Newman on union health centers in general and the ILGWU Center in particular. The publications of the Union Health Center primarily document the educational efforts of the center, providing information about the center, its services, and its activities. Also included are pamphlets about the ILGWU's health and welfare benefits program and publications from the Joint Board of Sanitary Control.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/060: ILGWU Union Health Center Records
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Women's clothing industry -- New York (State) -- New York; Women's clothing industry -- Employees -- Medical care -- United States; Women's clothing industry -- Employees -- Medical care -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Industrial relations -- United States; Industrial relations -- New York (State) -- New York; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Union Health Center.
5512047
- Health and Welfare Benefits Program of the ILGWU, 1951-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  In English and French
  - Item 1: Health, Welfare, Recreation and Death Benefits: Group I. Rules and Regulations, Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    By Southwestern Region Health and Welfare Fund. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Health, Welfare, Recreation and Death Benefits: Group II. Rules and Regulations, Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 3: Health, Welfare, Recreation and Death Benefits: Group III. Rules and Regulations, Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 4: Better Medical Care That You Can Afford, Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    By Educational Department. Item is in English.
  - Item 5: Let's See, Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    By U.S. Public Health Service. Workers' Health Series, no.12. Item is in English.
  - Item 6: A Member's Guide to Health, Welfare and Retirement Benefits, Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    September 1, 1978. Third edition. Item is in English.
  - Item 7: Guide des Benefices de Sante, de bein-etre et de pension de retraite, Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    September 1, 1978. Third edition. Item is in French.
  - Item 8: A Summary of Benefits, Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    By Health and Welfare Benefits Program of the Eastern Region. 2 copies. Item is in English.
- The Thread of Life, ILGWU Health and Welfare Services Pamphlet, 1956; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: The Thread of Life, ILGWU Health and Welfare Services Pamphlet, Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
    By Health and Welfare Services. Item is in English.
- Joint Board of Sanitary Control and Union Health Center Pamphlets, 1913-1949; Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: Workers' Health Bulletin, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. 3 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Second Annual Report, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. December, 1912. Item is in English.
  - Item 3: Five Years' Work and Progress, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. October 31, 1910 - October 31, 1915. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 4: Seating and Posture, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. Item is in English.
  - Item 5: Eleventh Annual Report, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 6: Report to 1922 Convention I.L.G.W.U., Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Union Health Center. Item is in English.
  - Item 7: Seventh Year Work and Progress, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. October 31, 1917. Item is in English.
  - Item 8: Report, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    pages 3-10. Item is in English.
  - Item 9: Third Annual Report, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. December, 1913. Item is in English.
  - Item 10: First Annual Report, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. October, 1911. Item is in English.
  - Item 11: Fourth Annual Report, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. October 31, 1910 - October 31, 1914. Item is in English.
  - Item 12: Ceremonies and Inspection of Facilities Marking Completion of Expansion Program, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Union Health Center. February 19, 1949. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 13: Cooperative Health, Medical and Dental Service, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 14: Annual Report, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Garment Industry Medical Center. Item is in English.
  - Item 15: Interim Report, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 16: Annual Report, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 17: Annual Report, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 18: Triennial Report, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 19: Union Health Center, 1913-1940, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Union Health Center. May, 1940. Item is in English.
  - Item 20: Security on the March, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Health and Welfare Services. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 21: Report to 23rd Convention I.L.G.W.U., Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Union Health Center. May, 1937. Item is in English.
  - Item 22: Report for 1930, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Union Health Center. 3 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 23: Report of the Director for 1936, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By George M. Price; Union Health Center. January 29, 1937. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 24: Triennial Report, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 25: Workers' and Their Teeth Troubles, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 26: Rules Governing the Tuberculosis Fund, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Adopted November, 1920. Item is in English.
  - Item 27: To Your Health!, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Allentown-Easton Health Center. Item is in English.
  - Item 28: Directory of Certificated Shops in the Cloak, Suit and Skirt Industry, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. May, 1913. Item is in English.
  - Item 29: Bulletin, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. no.10 (1913:Sept.). Item is in English.
  - Item 30: Official Opening New Building and Health Center, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    November 17, 1951.. Item is in English.
  - Item 31: Union Benefits: Medical and Other Benefits in Labor Organizations, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By George M. Price. Bulletin no.3 (1918). Presented to ILGWU Convention, May 20, 1918. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 32: Overweight?, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Fire Hazards in Factory Buildings Pamphlets, 1915-1923; Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: Fire Hazards in Factory Buildings Pamphlets, Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
    By George M. Price; Joint Board of Sanitary Control. Bulletin no.8 (1915). Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Fire Hazards in Factory Buildings Pamphlets, Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
    By George M. Price; Rudolph P. Miller; Joint Board of Sanitary Control. Item is in English.
- Union Health Center Pamphlets, 1912-1949; Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: Commemoration: Fiftieth Anniversary First Union Health Center in the United States, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    June 5, 1964. Includes lyrics to song "The Man Who Rose In Texas." Tribute to Lyndon Johnson (LBJ). Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Bulletin, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. no.6 (1912:May). Item is in English.
  - Item 3: Bulletin, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. no.7 (1913:May). Item is in English; Yiddish.
  - Item 4: Light and Illumination in Garment Shops, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By George M. Price; Davis H. Tuck. no.2 (1918). 3 sopies. Item is in English.
  - Item 5: The Union Health Center: Questions and Answers, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Pauline M. Newman. Item is in English.
  - Item 6: Local 60 Health Plan, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Local 60. Item is in English.
  - Item 7: Union Health Center, 1913-1933, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Union Health Center. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 8: Medical Department; Dental Clinic, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 9: Welcome to Your Union Health Center, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Item is in English.
  - Item 10: Shop Chairmen!, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 11: Union Health Center: A Short Address, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By George M. Price; Union Health Center. 4 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 12: Der Yunion Helt Senter, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Union Health Center. 3 copies. Item is in Yiddish.
  - Item 13: Union Health Center Ceremonies, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Press release. 3 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 14: Dinner: Fourth Anniversary of the Foundation, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 15: New Union Health Plan, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Leo Price; Union Health Center. Reprinted from Industrial Medicine, February, 1945. Item is in English.
  - Item 16: Medical Examination Health Information, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 17: Budget Report for Union Health Center Executive Board Committee, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Union Health Center. April 27, 1948. Item is in English.
  - Item 18: Conference on "Labor and Health", Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Union Health Center. April 14, 1931. Item is in English.
  - Item 19: The Growth of an Idea: The Union Health Center, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Union Health Center. May, 1939. Item is in English.
  - Item 20: Board Meeting, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Union Health Center. July 26, 1949. Item is in English.
  - Item 21: Response to question from New York State Temporary Commission to Formulate a Health Plan, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Leo Price; Union Health Center. December 16, 1938. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 22: Graphic Report of the Health Programs of ILGWU Locals, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 23: Annual Meeting, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Union Health Center. March 10, 1944. Item is in English.
- Pauline Newman Pamphlet, Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Item 1: Pauline Newman Pamphlet, Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Manufacturers' Bulletin for Fire Protection Pamphlet, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
  March
  - Item 1: Manufacturers' Bulletin for Fire Protection Pamphlet, Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. March, 1915. 2 copies. Item is in English.
- Union Health Center Graphic Report of the Health Programs of ILGWU Locals, 1940; Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Item 1: Union Health Center Graphic Report of the Health Programs of ILGWU Locals, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Union Health Center. Second copy. Hard bound and engraved for David Dubinsky. Item is in English.
- A Health Education Program for Garment Workers. Report and Recommendations of the Educational Department of the Joint Board of Sanitary Control, 1920; Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
  April 15
  - Item 1: A Health Education Program for Garment Workers. Report and Recommendations of the Educational Department of the Joint Board of Sanitary Control, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. April 15, 1920. 2 copies. Item is in English.
- "Eyesight Conservation in the Garment Industry" by Leo Price, Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Item 1: Eyesight Conservation in the Garment Industry, Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    By Leo Price; Union Health Center. Occupational Aspects of Ophthamology, course in Graduate Ophthamology. Photocopy. Item is in English.
- Union Health Center Employee Handbook and Press Releases, 1949-1963; Publication (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: Employee Handbook, Publication (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Item 2: William Green address at Union Health Center Ceremony, Publication (Box 2, Folder 1)
    By William Green; Union Health Center. February 19, 1949. Press Release. Item is in English.
- Description of the Health and Welfare Programs of All ILGWU Affiliates, 1966; Publication (Box 2, Folder 2)
  September
  - Item 1: Description of the Health and Welfare Programs of All ILGWU Affiliates, Publication (Box 2, Folder 2)
    September, 1966.. Item is in English.
- Union Health Center Pamphlets, 1913-1956; Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: Mogen Fadshtapung, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Item 2: Fun El Ht Vert Men Nit Vet, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Item 3: Medal for a Union: Fifty Years of the ILGWU Union Health center, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Item 4: Afiel fun des Yunion Helt Senter, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
    By Union Health Center. 2 copies. Item is in Yiddish.
  - Item 5: Your Union Health Center, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
    By Union Health Center. Item is in English; Chinese.
  - Item 6: Shop Conditions, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
    By Local 23-25. Item is in English; Chinese.
  - Item 7: Bollettino Sanitario Dell'Operaio, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. Item is in Italian.
  - Item 8: Local 85 News, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
    By Local 85. v.1:no.2 (1956:May). Item is in English.
  - Item 9: Union Health Center, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
    By Union Health Center. Flyer. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 10: Dental Department of the Union Health Center, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Item 11: Applicants to the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Item 12: A Buletin fun di Arbeyter's Gezundheyt, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. 3 copies. Item is in Yiddish.
  - Item 13: Bulletin, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. May, 1914. Item is in English.
  - Item 14: The Union Health Center of the I.L.G.W.U., Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
    By Pauline M. Newman. 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 15: Centro de Salud de la Union, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
    By Union Health Center. Item is in Spanish.
  - Item 16: Union Health Center ILGWU, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
    By Union Health Center. Item is in Chinese.
  - Item 17: The Union Health Center: The Health Department of Organized Labor. Twenty-First Annivesary, 1913-1934, Publication (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "Five Years' Experience with a New Mobile Health Survey Program." ILGWU Health and Welfare Department, 1952; Publication (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: Five Years' Experience with a New Mobile Health Survey Program. ILGWU Health and Welfare Department, Publication (Box 2, Folder 4)
    By James Bloom. Item is in English.
- "Health Survey of Workers in Garment Industry as Part of Preventative Medicine Program", 1951; Publication (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: Health Survey of Workers in Garment Industry as Part of Preventative Medicine Program, Publication (Box 2, Folder 5)
    By Joseph H. Kaplan; Nathaniel N. Bennett; Grace Foley. Item is in English.
- Tuberculosis Articles, 1925; Publication (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Item 1: Rules Governing the Tuberculosis Fund, Publication (Box 2, Folder 6)
    November, 1920. 3 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Labor's Fight Against Tuberculosis, Publication (Box 2, Folder 6)
    By George M. Price. Reprinted from the Transactions of the Twenty-First Annual Meeting of the National Tuberculosis Association, 1925. Item is in English.
  - Item 3: Tuberculosis: A Labor Problem, Publication (Box 2, Folder 6)
    By Leo Price. Reprinted from The American Review of Tuberculosis, v.54:no.6 (1946:Dec.). Item is in English.
- Union Health Center Articles, 1911-1968; Publication (Box 2, Folder 7)
  In English, Italian, and Yiddish
  - Item 1: Report, Publication (Box 2, Folder 7)
    By Union Health Center. v.1:no.1, 3-5 (1944-1945). Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Sanitary Control Bulletin, Publication (Box 2, Folder 7)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. v.2:no.1 (1920:Jan.). 2 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 3: Union-Sponsored Health Clinics, Publication (Box 2, Folder 7)
    By Elizabeth McFadden. Reprinted from Newark Sunday News Magazine, January 2, 1955. Item is in English.
  - Item 4: UHC Physician Staff Depletion and Budget, Publication (Box 2, Folder 7)
    By Milton Arons. July 25, 1968. Item is in English.
  - Item 5: Union Health Center News, Publication (Box 2, Folder 7)
    By Union Health Center. v.3:no.1 (1952:Jan.). Item is in English.
  - Item 6: Your Union Health Center, Publication (Box 2, Folder 7)
    By Union Health Center. Flyer.. Item is in English.
  - Item 7: The Labor Union's Responsibility, Publication (Box 2, Folder 7)
    By Leo Price. Reprinted from Industrial Medicine, July, 1944. Item is in English.
  - Item 8: Report of Survey of the Union Health Center, Publication (Box 2, Folder 7)
    By New York State Department of Social Welfare. 3 copies. Item is in English.
  - Item 9: Bollettine della Giunta Riunita del Controllo Sanitario, Publication (Box 2, Folder 7)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. no.2 (1911:July). Item is in Italian.
  - Item 10: Buletin, Publication (Box 2, Folder 7)
    By Joint Board of Sanitary Control. No.8 (1913:March 15). Item is in Yiddish.
- Union Health Center Yearly Report, 1941; Publication (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Item 1: Union Health Center Yearly Report, Publication (Box 2, Folder 8)
    By Union Sanatorium Association. Item is in English.
- Union Health Center Journal, 1924; Publication (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Item 1: Union Health Center Journal, Publication (Box 2, Folder 9)
    By Union Health Center. no.1 (1924:March 10). 4 copies. Item is in English.
- Text digitized from the collection., Publication (Box 3)